Guide to the Frank D. Brown Family Papers 1865-1950
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana-Missoula
Frank D. Brown family papers
1865-1950
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 037
Brown, Frank D. (Frank Dean), 1845-1931
3.5 linear feet
The Frank D. Brown Family Papers include Frank D. Brown's business correspondence, financial records, insurance company records, Society of Montana Pioneers records and correspondence, writings, photos, and memorabilia. It also includes a small amount of his son, James M. Brown's, personal correspondence and letters related to the Sons and Daughters of Montana Pioneers as well as Rutledge and Albertina Brown Parker's correspondence with Sons and Daughters of Montana Pioneers, and a few insurance and legal issues.
Biographical Note
Known as Frank D. "Sandbar" Brown throughout his life in Montana, Brown was born John Francis Deane Brown in Nelson County, Virginia on November 24, 1845. In June 1861 he enlisted in the Confederate Army and served until his discharge in September 1862. He re-enlisted, this time in the marine service. Capture by the Union Army ended his military career in April 1863. Brown was paroled and transported to St. Louis where he booked passage on a steamer to Fort Union on the upper Missouri River and then on to Fort Benton in Montana Territory by December 1865. It was also about this time that Brown permanently dropped "John" from his name in response to an increasing distaste for the Union Army's marching song "John Brown's body lies a mouldering in the ground..."
In Montana Territory he worked as a fur trapper, scout and a placer miner. In 1873, A. J. Davis hired Brown, who then located the Lexington and other mines. In 1878, Brown moved to Philipsburg and worked for mining firms in the area. During the next forty years he managed and developed many of the well-known placer and quartz mines in the area. He was also owner and editor of the Philipsburg Mail and gained his nickname of "Sandbar" through the signing of many articles with that title.
Brown attended all Democratic party state conventions for over 40 years. He was also a member of the Sons of the American Revolution and the major-general commanding the northwest division of the United Confederate Veterans for the states of Montana, the Dakotas, Idaho, Wyoming and Washington.
Brown was an active member of the Society of Montana Pioneers and in 1908 was elected as its historian, an office he held, except for one year, until his death in 1931. In 1923 he was also elected as secretary of the organization. Within the Society, he was instrumental in determining locations and erecting monuments marking significant historical events, including marking the path of the Mullan Road. A son, James M. Brown, and daughter, Albertina (Tina) Brown Parker, were active in the Sons and Daughters of Montana Pioneers.
Brown married Anna Elizabeth Lentz in Helena, Montana, on December 1873. They had eight children: Frances Dean, Anna, Edward Wilhelm, Amy Frances, Albertina Nettie, Minnie Madeline, Angus, and James A. Murray. Francis Dean, Anna, and Angus died before the age of three. Anna Lentz Brown died on October 6, 1914.
During his later years, Brown was a rancher and also worked in real estate and insurance. He died in Missoula, Montana, on January 16, 1931.
The Frank D. Brown Family Papers include Frank D. Brown's business correspondence, a few personal letters, financial records, insurance registers, Society of Montana Pioneers records and correspondence, his historical, fiction, and speech writings, photos, and memorabilia. Series II, James M. Brown, includes personal correspondence and letters related to the Sons and Daughters of Montana Pioneers. Series III, Rutledge and Albertina Brown Parker, includes correspondence with Sons and Daughters of Montana Pioneers, insurance and legal issues.
This collection has been divided into three series:
Series I: Frank D. Brown, 1865-1950, 3.3 linear feet
Subseries 1: Correspondence, 1892-1930, 1.2 linear feet
Subseries 2: Financial Records, Mining Reports, and Legal Documents, 1887-1924, 1.2 linear feet
Subseries 3: Society of Montana Pioneers, 0.2 linear feet, 1865-1931
Subseries 4: Speeches and Writings, 1898-1920, 0.2 linear feet
Subseries 5: Photographs, 1875-1932, 0.4 linear feet
Subseries 6: Miscellaneous, 1917-1950, 0.1 linear feet
Series II: James M. Brown, 1910-1935, 0.2 linear feet
Series III: Rutledge and Albertina Brown Parker, 1924-1948, 1 folder
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
The papers were held by the family until the time of the donation.
Donated by Virginia (Ginger) Brown, daughter of James M. Brown, 1969.
The Montana Historical Society holds the Society of Montana Pioneers and the Society of Sons and Daughters of Montana Pioneers Records. Other family members, Francis C. Brown and Margaret Cabell Brown Loughborough donated family papers to Georgetown University Library where they are held as the Loughborough Family Papers.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Parker, Rutledge, 1877-1969
Frontier and pioneer life--Montana--Philipsburg; Mines and mineral resources--Montana--Philipsburg; Businessme--Montan--Philipsburg
Business records--Montana--Philipsburg
Montana; Pioneers; Mines and Mineral Resources
- Frank D. Brown, 1865-1950; Series I; 3.3 linear feet
  Series I, Frank D. Brown, is divided into six subseries reflecting the type or theme of the materials included. Subseries 1 includes correspondence about his mining work and partnerships, a small amount of personal correspondence mostly with his daughter, Albertina (Tina) Brown, and letters related to his activities and interest in the Society of Montana Pioneers. Brown corresponded frequently with James A. Murray, Butte banker, investor and uncle of James E. Murray; Paul A. Fusz, mine owner; C.D. McClure, one of the owners of the Granite Mountain and Bi-Metallic Mines; and W.A. Clark, Montana copper baron. Subseries 2 includes financial records relevant to Brown's mining businesses, reports on various mines, insurance registers for his Philipsburg, Montana, based insurance company, and a few legal documents. Subseries 3 reflects his long time membership in the Society of Montana Pioneers and his efforts to establish historical monuments and records of significant events in Montana history. It also includes a copy of the 1865 receipt that served as proof of Brown's arrival in Montana. Subseries 4 holds Brown's historical writings about Montana, his fiction about forest animals and also stories set in foreign locales, and speeches about Montana history. Subseries 5 includes photos of the Brown Family, the Society of Montana Pioneers, friends and dignatories as well as Philipsburg and Helena locations. Subseries 6 includes biographical information, news clippings about Brown, Montana pioneers, and Montana history, a few pieces about the United Confederate Veterans, and memorabilia.
  - Correspondence, 1892-1930; Subseries 1; 1.2 linear feet
    - General outgoing correspondence and reports, 1898-1909 (Box-volume OS 1/Volume 1)
    - Outgoing correspondence mostly to C.D. McLure, 1899-1903 (Box-volume OS 1/Volume 2)
    - Outgoing correspondence to C.D. McLure, March-July, 1903 (Box-volume OS 2/Volume 3)
    - Outgoing correspondence to Paul A. Fusz, 1903-1904 (Box-volume OS 2/Volume 4)
    - General outgoing correspondence, 1898-1919 (Box-folder 3/1)
    - General outgoing correspondence, 1920-1930 (Box-folder 3/2)
    - Incoming correspondence, 1892 (Box-folder 3/3)
    - Incoming correspondence, 1898-1914 (Box-folder 3/4)
    - Incoming correspondence, 1915 (Box-folder 3/5)
    - Incoming correspondence, 1916 (Box-folder 3/6)
    - Incoming correspondence, 1917 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Incoming correspondence, 1918 (Box-folder 3/8)
    - Incoming correspondence, 1919-1930 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Financial Records, Mining Reports, and Legal Documents, 1887-1924; Subseries 2; 1.2 linear feet
    - Ledger, 1887-1905 (Volume 5)
    - Ledger, 1894-1904 (Volume 6)
    - Ledger, 1894-1899 (Volume 7)
    - Day Book, 1887-1890 (Volume 8)
    - Insurance register, 1886-1899 (Volume 9)
    - Insurance register, 1895-1897 (Volume 10)
    - Miscellaneous invoices and receipts, 1890-1924 (Box-folder 3/10)
    - Report of Brickley Group mining claims, undated (Box-folder 3/11)
    - Report of Hawkeye Group mining claims, 1907-1917 (Box-folder 3/12)
    - Henderson Gulch mineral and mining conditions report, undated (Box-folder 3/13)
    - Sapphire deposits, Yogo, McLure and Fusz reports, 1904 (Box-folder 3/14)
    - Shields River Timber report, undated (Box-folder 3/15)
    - Smith Creek Timber reports, undated (Box-folder 3/16)
    - Tuscumbia Mining Company, 1911 (Box-folder 3/17)
    - Northwest Mining Association, Proceedings of the First Annual Convention, 1895 (Box-folder 3/18)
    - Maps, undated (Box-folder 3/19)
    - Legal documents, 1897-1923 (Box-folder 3/20)
  - Society of Montana Pioneers, 1865-1931; Subseries 3; 0.2 linear feet
    - Fort Union receipt for purchase of grubstake, 1865 (Box-folder 3/21)
    - Society of Montana Pioneers membership certificate, 1901 (Box-folder 3/22)
    - Society of Montana Pioneers applications and membership list, 1924-1931 (Box-folder 3/23)
    - Minutes of the Society of Montana Pioneers, 1923 (Box-volume 4/1)
    - Report of the historian of the Society of Montana Pioneers, 1921-1925 (Box-volume 4/2)
    - Society of Montana Pioneers officers and report of historian, 1916-1927 (Box-folder 4/3)
    - Soeity of Montana Pioneers meeting programs, 1923-1930 (Box-folder 4/4)
    - Society of Montana Pioneers stationery, undated (Box-folder 4/5)
  - Speeches and writings, 1898-1920; Subseries 4; 0.2 linear feet
    - Essays and stories about Montana, undated (Box-folder 4/6)
    - Essays and stories, undated (Box-folder 4/7)
    - Incomplete stories and writings, undated (Box-folder 4/8)
    - Speeches, 1898-1920 (Box-folder 4/9)
  - Photographs, 1875-1932; Subseries 4; 0.4 line
    - Frank D. Brown, circa 1875 (Box-folder 4/10)
    - Frank D. Brown, circa 1880 (Box-folder 4/11)
    - Frank D. Brown, 1902 (Box-folder 4/12)
    - Frank D. Brown with horses, circa 1900 (Box-folder 4/13)
    - Frank D. Brown and A.L. Stone, circa 1915 (Box-folder 4/14)
    - Frank D. Brown's mother, undated (Box-folder 4/15)
    - Albertina (Tina) Brown with two other women, circa 1900 (Box-folder 4/16)
    - Albertina (Tina) Brown, circa 1900 (Box-folder 4/17)
    - Albertina (Tina) Brown, circa 1905 (Box-folder 4/18)
    - James M. Brown, circa 1895 (Box-folder 4/19)
    - Brown family, 1899 (Box-folder 4/20)
    - Women's basketball team in Philipsburg, Montana, 1903 (Box-folder 4/21)
    - John G. McClain, blacksmith, and his partner, 1914 (Box-folder 4/22)
    - D.M. Durfee, undated (Box-folder 4/23)
    - Mr. Kinney, high school instructor, undated (Box-folder 4/24)
    - Judge Forrest Titus, undated (Box-folder 4/25)
    - Connolly family, 1910 (Box-folder 4/26)
    - Mr. and Mrs. Botscheider, undated (Box-folder 4/27)
    - Miss Wolf, 1892 (Box-folder 4/28)
    - A.N. Whitlock, circa 1895 (Box-folder 4/29)
    - Panorama style group photos of Society of Montana Pioneers, 1919-1932 (Map-drawer OS 8)
    - Group photos of Society of Montana Pioneers, 1928 (Box-folder 5/1)
    - Group photo of Sons and Daughters of Montana Pioneers, 1928 (Box-folder 5/2)
    - Men on porch of building with advertisement for Democratic Party rally in Anaconda, Montana, 1894 (Box-folder 5/3)
    - Watch tower in Helena, Montana, circa 1900 (Box-folder 5/4)
    - Atlas Block building, Helena, Montana, circa 1900 (Box-folder 5/5)
    - Caterpillar tractor at the Philipsburg Mining Company, circa 1925 (Box-folder 5/6)
    - Hauling ore in horse drawn wagon from Iron Mine, Philipsburg, Montana, 1907-1917 (Box-folder 5/7)
    - Buildiing Forest Service fire lookout, circa 1900 (Box-folder 5/8)
    - Photo scrapbook style Christmas card, 1912 (Box-folder 5/9)
    - Reeder's Alley, Helena, Montana, circa 1900 (Box-folder 5/10)
    - Unidentified outdoor photos, undated (Box-folder 5/11)
    - Unidentified football team, 1900 (Box-folder 5/12)
    - Unidentified photos of men, undated (Box-folder 5/13)
    - Unidentified photos of women, undated (Box-folder 5/14)
    - Unidentified photos of children, undated (Box-folder 5/15)
    - Unidentified group photos, undated (Box-folder 5/16)
  - Miscellaneous, 1916-1950; Subseries 6; 0.1 linear feet
    - Biographical information, undated (Box-folder 5/17)
    - "The Old Green House" about the life of Frank Dean (Sandbar) Brown by his daughter, Amy Brown Spencer, circa 1950 (Box-folder 5/18)
    - Reunion of the United Confederate Veterans, Convention Proceedings, 1917 (Box-folder 5/19)
    - U.S. government publications regarding the Bureau of War Risk Insurance in the Treasury Department, 1917 (Box-folder 5/20)
    - Report of the canvas of the presidential primary in the State of Montana, 1924 (Box-folder 5/21)
    - Newsclipping scrapbook, circa 1890 (Box OS 6)
    - Newsclipping file, 1916-1931 (Map-drawer OS 7)
    - Memorabilia, undated (Box-folder 5/22)
- James M. Brown, 1910-1935; Series II; 0.2 linear feet
  Series II, James M. Brown, includes personal correspondence and correspondence related to the Sons and Daughters of Montana Pioneers.
  - Incoming correspondence, 1910 (Box-folder 5/23)
  - Incoming correspondence from father, Frank D. Brown, 1917-1918 (Box-folder 5/24)
  - General correspondence regarding the Sons and Daughters of Montana Pioneers, 1928-1931 (Box-folder 5/25)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1934-1935 (Box-folder 5/25)
  - High school and college memorabilia, 1910-1911 (Box-folder 5/26)
- Rutledge and Albertina Brown Parker, 1924-1948; Series III; 1 folder
  Series III, Rutledge and Albertina Brown Parker, includes correspondence related to Sons and Daughters of Montana Pioneers, insurance and legal issues.
  - Correspondence, 1924-1948 (Box-folder 5/28)